Albert de Rochas Papers 1845-1921 1882-1908 Mss.Ms.Coll.106
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, Bulk, 1882-1908; 1845-1916; 1.25 lin. feet
  - Rochas D'Aiglun, Eugene Auguste Albert -- "Les Fantomes des Vivants," Sciences Psychique 5 (1905): 257-272, 1895; Pr. Ms, 15p. (Box 2)
  - Rochas D'Aiglun, Eugene Auguste Albert -- "Nouvelles expériences relatives au coprs astal et au rapport magnétique," La Vie Nouvelle, n.d.; Newspaper clipping, 2p. (Box 2)
  - Rochas D'Aiglun, Eugene Auguste Albert -- Psychic research. Notes, n.d.; AMs, 10p. (Box 2)
    Notes of "suggestions abstraits," transport of sensibility, photographic evidence.
  - Rochas D'Aiglun, Eugene Auguste Albert -- "Le Rêve", n.d.; AMs and Pr. Ms, 15p. (Box 2)
    Source uncertain.
  - Rochas D'Aiglun, Eugene Auguste Albert -- "Les sentiments, la musique et le geste," Journal d'Études Psychologiques, 1901; Page proof (Box 2)
  - Rochas D'Aiglun, Eugene Auguste Albert -- "Les vies successives", n.d.; Pr. Ms, 4p. (Box 2)
  - [Rochas d'Aiglun, Edouard Eugène Louis de. Death notice], 1899 May 5; Pr. Ms, 1p. (Box 2)
  - Rochas D'Aiglun, François Gabriel Henri -- Marriage contract with Marie Madeleine Claire Caillard, 1901 Aug. 3; DS, 4p. (Box 2)
  - Rossolowsko, W., 1901 May 20; ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
    Aksakoff's health. Translation of the Seherin von Prevorst.
  - Rostoptchine, Lydie, 1900; 4 items (Box 2)
    Includes 2 ALsS, ANS, List.
  - Rostoptchine, Lydie -- Une Matinée chez Madame Adam en 1900, par la contesse Lydie Rostoptchine, AMs, 10p. (Box 2)
  - [Rothschild, James de]. Le Baron James de Rothschild, n.d.; Pr. Ms, 8p. (Box 2)
    With frontis. engr. of Rothschild. Source uncertain, signed (in print) Morgand et Fatout.
  - Saint Antoine de Padove, n.d.; AMs, 12p. (Box 2)
    Probably part of longer mss (pages numbered beginning 5).
  - Sanchez, F., 1896 Dec. 20; ALS, 3p. (Box 2)
  - Sassan, Angèle Autine, 1897 June 6; ALS, 3p. (Box 2)
  - [Saul, H.]?, n.d.; 3 ALsS (Box 2)
  - Sausse, Henri -- Le Spiritisme à Lyon (Saint-Amand, Switzerland: Daniel-Chambon, 1905), Pam., 26p. (Box 2)
  - Schrenk-Notzing, Albert Philibert Franz, 1901 June 18 (Box 2)
  - Schrenk-Notzing, Albert Philibert Franz -- "Telepathische experimente des Sonderausschusses der Psychologischen Gesellschaft zu München," Sphinx, 1887; Offprint, 11p. (Box 2)
    Experiments with Lina.
  - Scymon, R.(?), 1885 Dec. 22; ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
  - Sebert, Gen., 1892 May 4; ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
  - Sue, Eugene, 1846 Oct. 24; ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
    Letter to Eugene Sue from a German admirer, "E."
  - Sulzbach, M., n.d.; ALS, 3p. (Box 2)
  - Thesosophy, 1905; 3 items (Box 3)
    Includes AMs, Phénomênes de régressions de la mémorie and ALsS from D. A. Corumes (Mar. 25, 1905) and C. Remise (May 23, 1905)
  - Thomassins, Gen., 1892 Nov. 20; ALS, 1p. (Box 2)
  - Tissot, James, 1895 Oct. 28; ALS, 2p. (Box 3)
  - La Tribute Psychique no. 113 (1906), 1906 Sept.; Mag., 8p. (Box 3)
    With article on seances with medium M. Miller.
  - La Tribute Psychique no. 116 (1906), 1906 Dec.; Mag., 8p. (Box 3)
    More on medium Miller.
  - Ulmès, J. d', 1907 Feb. 15; ALS, 4p. (Box 3)
    Mention of Lina, "l'hypnotisée."
  - Valière, Laurent, 1903 Nov. 12; ALS, 4p. (Box 3)
  - Van der Naillen, A., 1902-1906; 7 ALsS (Box 3)
    Mention of Thomassins, Bailey, Reichel, Miller; Spiritualism in California.
  - Van Rutten, A., 1897 June 8; ALS, 1p. (Box 3)
  - Vaud(?) G., 1889 Mar. 11; ALS, 3p. (Box 3)
  - Vaux-Royer, Rose M., 1901 June 14; ALS, 2p. (Box 3)
    Queries on telepathy and psychic research from the Bureau of Psychic Research f the One Hundred Year Club.
  - Viard, G., 1904 Jan. 23; ALS, 3p. (Box 3)
  - Vicat, C., 1899 Apr. 27; ALS, 2p. (Box 3)
  - Villeneuve, M. de, 1895 July 4; ALS, 3p. (Box 3)
  - Villewitz, T. de, 1903 Feb. 26; ALS, 4p. (Box 3)
  - Virien, Mis de, 1895-1900; 2 ALsS (Box 3)
    Compliments on Rochas' exteriorisation of sensibility.
  - Visani Scozzi, Paolo, 1897-1898; 3 ALsS (Box 3)
    In Italian (one with translation into French). Re: Eusapia Paladino, Camille Flammarion.
  - Vitte, P., 1894-1896; 6 ALsS (Box 3)
  - Volpi, E., 1901 Nov. 18; PC, 1p. (Box 3)
  - Waldner de Freundstein, Thuret contesse de, 1902 Apr. 22-May 1; 3 ALsS (Box 3)
    Mention of Eusapia Paladino.
  - Wallace, Alfred Russel -- "Étude sur les apparitions" Annales des Sciences Psychiques, n.d.; Pr. Ms., 30p. (Box 3)
  - Watraszewski, Xavier de, 1898 Sept. 18; ALS, 4p. (Box 3)
    Eusapia Paladino.
  - Wendelstadt, Albertine, baronne de, 1900; 5 items (Box 3)
  - Willenewitz, M., n.d.; ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
  - Wiszniewski, 1898 Mar. 14-1900 July 25; 2 ALsS (Box 3)
    Seances with Mme Corner, reference to William Crookes and Kaite King.
  - Witte, Gen., 1898 Sept. 21; ALS, 3p. (Box 3)
  - Wladimiroff, Cécile de, 1908 June 23; ALS, 3p. (Box 3)
  - Wrchovsky, Guillaume, 1907 Apr. 14; ALS, 3p. (Box 3)
    Hypnotism and regression; Indians.
  - Wulff, Gen., 1889 Dec. 29; ALS, 2p. (Box 3)
  - Yve-Plessis, R., 1899 Dec. 23-26; 3 items (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d.; 11 items (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous: calling cards and invitations, 13 items (Box 3)
  - Illegible and unidentified, 1862 May 2-1910 Jan. 27; 17 items (Box 3)
- Series II. Photographs, 1873-1921; 0.5 lin. feet
  Rochas evidently placed a great importance on photography as a means of documenting elusive spiritual and psychic phenomena, and the Rochas Papers includes 69 photographs depicting spirits, psychic forces, séances, mediums, and "sensitives" taken between ca.1875 and 1900. Spirit photographs seem to have been of particular interest, and his papers include two interesting images taken by the famed (and debunked) Parisian Eugène Buguet, two prints of the spirit Bien Boa (a "Brahmin" materialized by the medium Marthe Béraud), and several other images, the most intriguing of which was taken in Elizabeth, N.J., of Elena de Obarrio, in which her guardian spirit and the spirit of her sleeping (and very much alive) brother also appear. This image was taken by, or with the assistance of the Cuban medium J. R. Simoni. Rochas also kept photographs of a séance conducted by Guy de Fontenay with Eusapia Paladino at Montfor l'Amaury, July 1897, including two cabinet cards of a séance in progress and a psychically-produced image of Paladino's face.
  Less common are a suite of photographs that demonstrate the reality of psychic forces. A fine carte de visite of Gustave Flaschoen taken by the British photographer Brittlebank displays the "force psychique sortant de ses mains," while three cartes provide a dramatic illustration of psychic force being generated by a circle held by the medium John Beattie in Bristol, England. The photographs Rochas collected of "sensitives" reflect his interests in the physical effects of art and music and his interest in the experience of religious or spiritual ecstasy.
  Other images document psychic forces in less concrete ways. The collection includes a series of 11 images associated with the Romanian psychic investigator Bogdan Hasdeu-Istrati (see also his correspondence), 11 "doubles" of Mme. Lambert, sent to Rochas by the editor G. Delanne, and the image by Mme de Valpinson are generally difficult to interpret visually, while in those of Paolo Visani Scozzi (apparently mounted for public display) one can see dim faces arising from amorphous psychic clouds. Rochas was also not coincidentally interested in x-radiography, acquiring a very early (March 1897) x-radiograph of a hand, apparently kept as demonstration that photography could reveal structures otherwise hidden to the eye. Equally interesting are several images taken by the photographer Nadar, including five boudoir cards of Rochas himself with an astral body "obtenu par trucage."
  - "Photo obtenu par Mr. J. Beattie, en 1872, à Bristol Reçu de lui en Oct. 1873. A. Aksakof", 1873 Oct.; 4 cartes de visite; Beattie, John (Box 3)
    Depicting spirit circle with psychic force emanating from hands. Also includes halftone reproduction of three of the images.
  - Spirit Bien Boa, 1905; 2 silver prints; Béraud, Marthe (Box 3)
    Photos taken of spirit on Indian Brahmin materialized by medium Eva C. (Marthe Béraud) before investigator Charles Richet.
    - Spirit of Bien Boa appearing to medium Marthe Beraud., ca. 1890; 1.0 Photograph(s); View of figure with hood and loose clothes.
  - Extase religieuse par la premon de front, Cab. card; Blois (Box 3)
  - Dr. Flaschoen, "force psychique sortant de ses mains.", 1875; Carte de visite; Full length view of Dr. Flaschoen sitting at desk, "psychic force" coming from his hands.; Brittlebank, A. (Box 3)
    Possibly the artist Gustave Flaschoen?
  - Female spirit and photograph, 1875; Carte de visite; Buguet, Edouard-Isidore, 1840- (Box 3)
  - Dr. Puch et Mme Puch, 1875; Carte de visite; Buguet, Edouard-Isidore, 1840- (Box 3)
  - Photographe spirite du capitaine Volpi, n.d.; Cabinet card; Castellani, Federico (Box 3)
    Volpi with female spirit.
  - Chowasky, Gen., n.d.; Silver print (Box 3)
  - "Doubles" Photos sent by Delanne, taken of Mme. Lambert, 1906; 11 prints (Oversize 4)
  - Ecstatic, n.d.; 2 cartes, 2 enlargements (Box 3)
  - "Études photo magnétique d'hypnose", n.d.; 2 mounted albumens (Box 3)
    One depicts Rochas and female hypnotic subject, the other a woman (hypnotized?) painting at an easel.
  - Fakir, n.d.; Printing out print (Box 3)
  - Psychic photographs, 1893; 11 printing out prints; Hasdeu-Istrati, Bogdan Petriceicu, 1837-1907 (Box 3)
    Most enclosed in letter of 1895 Aug. 12
  - Karren, Mme. Musique. "Portrait de sensitif", n.d.; Boudoir card (Box 3)
  - Lina (photographs of 1. castle and 2. group of six persons in boat), 2 mounted albumen prints (Box 3)
  - "Corps astral obtenu par trucage", 1893; 5 boudoir cards; Nadar (Box 3)
  - "Photographie du corps fluidique de Mme Lambert (deux fantomes de droites)" and "Photographie du corps astral de Mme. Lambert", 1893 June 3; 2 boudoir cards; Nadar (Box 3)
  - Obarrio, Elena de. Mlle Elena de Obarrio incarnée. Spirite 1o son Gardien (à gauche) 2o son jeune frère (à droite, celui-ci dormait à cet instant dans sa maison située à 300 pas de la fotografie. Elizabet, New Jersey", 1875 Nov.; Carte de visite (Box 3)
    Medium J. R. Simoni of Cuba.
  - Paladino, Eusapia, 1897 July 27; 3 prints (Box 3)
    3 photos from seance with Guy de Fontenay at Montfor l'Amaury, July 1897: 2 cabinet cards of seance at table, psychic impression of face.
  - Unidentified miniatures, n.d.; 2 silver prints; Picardy, Charles (Box 3)
  - "Radiographie. Plaque impressionié pendant la nuit par les affleuves de l'abbé Gobart", 1894; Mounted p.o.p. (Box 3)
  - "Souvenir de baptême de l'air", 1921 Sept. 28; Silver print (Box 3)
    French officers in front of biplane.
  - Spirit photograph [unidentified image of two shrouded figures, n.d.; Printing out print (Box 3)
  - Valpinson, Mme de "[illeg.] obtenu par Mme de Valpinson. Je ne sais comment. Avec des plaques du Dr. Egbert Müller, Berlin...", n.d.; Boudoir card (Box 3)
  - Grn. Mickhail Efremovich Adamovich, n.d.; Carte de visite; Varenik and Vladimirov (Box 3)
  - X-radiograph of hand, 1897 Nov.; Silver print; Virien, Mis de (Oversize 4)
  - Visani-Scozzi, Paolo. Psychic photos from seances with comtesse Mainardi and Ugo Donati, 1898 Sept. 8-10; 6 prints (Box 4)
    Mounted in pairs with description.
  - Nadar astral portrait of Eugene Rochas, sitting., ca. 1890; 1.0 Photograph(s); Eugene Rochas seated, with "psychic force" surrounding him.
  - Nadar astral portrait of Eugene Rochas, standing., ca. 1890; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of man standing next to chair, "psychic force" surrounding him.
  - Séance with John Beattie, medium., 1872; 1 item; Four men sitting around table, "psychic force" visible in center of group and at top of photograph.
  - Transparent figure of female in robes beside table., ca. 1890; 1.0 Item(s); Full length view of transparent figure.
  - Spirit in death pose behind seated man., ca. 1890; 1.0 Item(s); Full length view of man seated, with spirit behind him.